Thiago de Paula Oliveira | CV

I'm an enthusiastic **biostatistician** with ten years of academic experience and a passion for data analysis to help people understand their data. I designed and conducted agricultural experiments, and I am an experienced professional in statistical modelling, working in different areas such as agriculture, sports, and genetics. I have produced peer-reviewed papers in those areas and written technical reports. In addition, I have exceptional analytical and communication skills to interact with clients and provide the desired output. I'm looking now for an exciting opportunity in the industry. For more information about me, please, visit my blog https://prof-thiagooliveira.netlify.app/.

Technical Skills

▶ Statistics: High statistical awareness, focusing on statistical modelling and data anal-

ysis. I've worked with generalized linear mixed models, splines, longitudinal data, concordance analysis, state-space approach, pedigree and genomic-based models, graphical models, and non-linear models. I have experience

with classical and Bayesian views.

▶ Genetics: I have experience in simulating **animal and plant breeding programmes** to

test and compare new schemes or evaluate how to improve genetic mean and variance. I also have experience in helping breeders with statistical analysis of real data using software/packages like blupf90, BGLR, JAGS,

and STAN.

▶ Sports: Theory and application of statistical methods to evaluate athlete perfor-

mance and clinical trials.

Agriculture: Planning experimental designs, analysis of entomologic and vegetable

production data

▶ R Packages: I am enthusiast in creating R packages or functions as a solution to stan-

dardize statistical analysis and delivery faster responses to clients. Some

of public packages: AlphaPart, AlphaSimR, lcc.

Dashboard:
I have skills in creating shiny dashboards as a solution for interactive data

visualization and analysis for clients. Example of public shiny app I devel-

oped: COVID-19 prediction, Experiment Design.

▶ GitHub: I am managing the Highlander Lab and AlphaGenes organizations. I handle

repositories, actions, projects, teams, and pull requests.

▶ HPC Servers: I have experience working with **high-performance computers** at the Uni-

versity of Edinburgh to do statistical analysis.

Software and Language Skills

Statistical computing: R, Shiny, RStudio, Bash, Maple, SageMath, C++, blupf90

▶ Computational programs: GitHub, LaTeX, Markdown, Office 365, Inkscape

Operational systems:
Unix|Linux, Mac, Windows

▶ Languages: Portuguese (native), English

I worked together with partners from different companies and universities over the last few years. Some examples:

▶ ORRECO: I supported and delivered statistical models and dashboards to measure

athlete performance.

Aspire Academy: Long-term athlete's performance forecast on several Olympic sports.

also delivered a dashboard that shows descriptive statistics and statistical

quantities of interest.

▶ Limagrain: development of maize breeding programmes and statistical modelling

With those interactions, I've developed some skills such as i) ability to lead meetings and communicate professionally and positively; and ii) how to listen and understand client needs.

Professional Experience

1 1010331	bilai Experience		
2020-Actual	Researcher Fellow	University of Edinburgh	
	 PI: Dr. Gregor Gorjanc Quantitative genetics and genomics of plant breeding The Roslin Institute 		
2019-2020 (14 months)	Postdoc in Biostatistics	NUIGalway	
	 PI: Prof. Dr. John Newell and Prof. Dr. Carl Scarrott Aspire Academy research collaboration project, Statistical modelling for optimizing athlete performance, and early detection of secondary waves of Covid-19 infections. School of Mathematics, Statistics & Applied Maths; and Insight Centre for Data Analytics 		
2017 – 2019	Assistant Professor at University of São Paulo – ESALQ/USP (18 months)		

Fducation

Education	1	
2014 - 2018 (4 years)	PhD in Statistics	University of São Paulo – ESALQ/USP
	 Title: Estimating the longitudinal concordance correlation the components of polynomial mixed-effects regression model Advisor: Dr. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi and Prof. John Hinde Department of Exact Sciences 	rough fixed effects and variance
2016 (3 months)	Visiting scholar – internship	NUIGalway
	➤ Supervisor: Prof. John Hinde	
	▶ School of Mathematics, Statistics and Applied Mathematics	
	▶ Development of new methodology in Concordance Analysis	
2012 - 2014	MSc in Statistics	University of São Paulo –
(2 years)		ESALQ/USP
. ,	Title: Mixed-effects models applied to hue peel color of papay an scanner and colorimeter over time	•

- Advisor: Dr. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi
- Department of Exact Sciences

2007 – 2012 BSc in Agricultural Engineering (5 years)

University of São Paulo – ESALQ/USP

- ▶ Title: Calibration of scanner methodology to evaluate 'Golden' papaya peel color.
- Advisor: Dr. Silvio Sandoval Zocchi
- ▶ Department of Exact Sciences

>>> Teaching and Supervision

2017-2018 Teaching experience in **Experimental Statistics** and **Calculus** at the University of São Paulo.

In addition, I worked with students from Agricultural Engineering, Forest Engineering, and Food

Science programmes.

Supervision Experience in **supervising** under- and post-graduate students.

Awards

2020	Marie Skłodowska-Curie COFUND Fellowship under the project "Quantitative genetics and genomics of plant breeding"
2010	Honorable Mention at the 18^{th} USP International Symposium of Undergraduate Research, University of São Paulo.

Most relevant publications

Preprint	Oliveira, T.P.; Obšteter, J.; Pocrnic, I.; Heslot, N.; Gorjanc, G. A method for partitioning trends in genetic mean and variance to understand breeding practices, BioRxiv , 2022. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.10.475603
Article	Lara, L.A.d.C.; Pocrnic, I.; Oliveira, T.P. ; Gaynor, C.; Gorjanc, G. Temporal and genomic analysis of additive genetic variance in breeding programmes, Heredity , 2021. DOI: 10.1038/s41437-021-00485-y
Article	Oliveira, T.P. ; Buinvels, G; Pedlar, C.; Newell, J. Modelling menstrual cycle length in athletes using state-space models, Scientific Reports , 11, 2021. DOI: 10.1038/s41598-021-95960-1
Article	Oliveira, T.P.; Moral, R. A.; Zocchi, S. S.; Demetrio, C. G. B; Hinde, J. Icc: an R package to estimate the concordance correlation, Pearson correlation, and accuracy over time. PeerJ . Accepted for publication in August of 2020. DOI: 10.7717/peerj.9850
Article	Popin, G. V.; Santos, A. K. B.; Oliveira, T.P. ; Camargo, P. B.; Cerri, C. E. P.; Siqueira-Neto; M. Sugarcane straw management for bioenergy: effects of global warming on greenhouse gas emissions and soil carbon storage. Mitigation and Adaptation Strategies for Global Change , 2019. Link: https://doi.org/10.1007/s11027-019-09880-7
Article	Esteves, M. B.; Kleina, H. T.; Sales, T. M.; Oliveira, T.P.; Lara, I. A. R.; Almeida, R. P. P.; Coletta-Filho, H. D.; Lopes, J. R. S. Transmission efficiency of <i>Xylella fastidiosa</i> subsp. <i>pauca</i> sequence types by sharpshooter vectors after <i>in vitro</i> acquisition. The American Phytopathological Society , v. 109, no.2, 2019. Link: https://doi.org/10.1094/PHYT0-07-18-0254-FI
Article	Oliveira, T.P.; Hinde, J.; Zocchi, S. S. Longitudinal Concordance Correlation Function Based on Variance Components: An Application in Fruit Color Analysis. Journal of Agricultural, Biological, and Environmental Statistics , v. 23, p. 233-254, 2018. Link: https://doi.org/10.1007/s13253-018-0321-1

Address: The Roslin Institute, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, Scotland. H91 TK33